Finding Aid for the James B. Coover Collection of Bibliographic Catalogs, 1690-1994
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
James B. Coover Collection of Bibliographic Catalogs, 1690-1994
Mus. Arc. 78
Coover, James, 1925-2004
7 boxes (157 items)
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
The collection chiefly consists of sales and auction catalogs from book and antiquarian dealers, with an emphasis on music. There are also some catalogs of personal collections included. Forty-nine of the items are photocopies and the remaining items are originals.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Gift of James and Jeanne Coover, 1992-1997.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Biographical Note
James Burrell Coover (1925-2004) was hired in 1967 by the State University of New York at Buffalo to become the first director of the Music Library. Previously he was the director of the George Sherman Dickinson Music Library at Vassar College 1953-1967 and Assistant Director of the Bibliographical Center for Research in Denver, Colorado 1950-1953. While at the University at Buffalo, Coover helped establish, with Carol June Bradley, a program in music librarianship that was responsible for training several generations of music librarians.
Coover's research resulted in several scholarly articles and the following books:
Music Lexicography Including a Study of Lacunae: 1500-1700 (1958)
Musical Instrument Collections: Catalogues and Cognate Literature (Detroit, 1981)
Music Publishing, Copyright, and Piracy in Victorian England (1985)
Antiquarians' Catalogues of Musical Interest (1988)
Private Music Collections: Catalogs and Cognate Literature (2001)
Scope and Content Note
The collection chiefly consists of sales and auction catalogs from book and antiquarian dealers, with an emphasis on music. There are also some catalogs of personal collections included. Forty-nine of the items are photocopies and the remaining items are originals. Many of the auction catalogs include annotations indicating buyer names and prices. Two binders in the collection contain photocopies of title pages of sales catalogs.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series:
I. Bibliographic catalogs
II. Binders
Container List
- Bibliographic catalogs, 1690-1994, I.; Items 1-155
  Arranged chronologically by either publication date or first date of sale.
  - Unidentified. Catalogue de la collection faite par Philidor garde de la musique de Louis XIV, par ordre de numeres…Ms. Copié sue celui de la Bibliothèque du Conservatoire de Paris…, 1690?, 13 unnumbered pages (Box 1, Item 001)
    France?: unpublished manuscript
    Photocopy
    Copy of MS in Bibliothèque royale de Belgique. "Ms. copié sur celui de la Bibliothèque du Conservatoire de Paris"--Fetis.
    Named collector(s): Philidor, André
  - Unidentified. Catalogue of ancient and modern Musick Books both vocal and instrumental, with divers treatises about the same, and several musical instruments … sold at Dewing's Coffee House in Popes-Head Alley…December the 17th, 1691, 1691-12-17, 16 pages (Box 1, Item 002)
    London (England): unidentified
    Various lottings. Perhaps the earliest English music auction catalogue.
  - Andries Voorstad (Frim). Catalogus van zeer fraije ende rare nederduitse boecken, als meede van uytnetmende partyen muzycg, musycg-instrumenten, prent-konst, insecta, als andere fraijigheden nagelaten by Leendert van Beke …, 1708-02-20, 20 pages (Box 1, Item 003)
    Delft (Netherlands): Andries Voorstad (Frim)
    154 lots of music. From Vereeniging ter Bervordering…, Amsterdam.
    Named collector(s): Beke, Leendert van
  - J.-T. Hérissant et J.-T. Hérissant fils. Catalogue des livres de la bibliothèque de feue Madame Pompadour, Dame du Palais de la Reine. Selections, 1765, pages 149-171, 381-399 (Box 1, Item 004)
    Paris (France): J.-T. Hérissant et J.-T. Hérissant fils
    Selections pertaining to music.
    Named collector(s): Pompadour, Jeanne Antoinette Poisson, marquise de
    Contains: Theatre de l'opera: Ballets, &c. -- Theatre italien & opera-comique -- Musique: Ballets & opera -- Cantates -- Airs & chansons -- Motets & sonates
  - Commer, Franz. Catalogus musicalium Godefridi Dunwalt, canonici collegi[atae ecclesiae] B. Mariae V., 1770, 137 pages (Box 1, Item 005)
    Cologne (Germany): unpublished manuscript
    Thematic index for 558 instrumental works. Copy of GB Lbm: Hirsch. IV 1081. Brook: entry 325.
    Named collector(s): Dunwalt, Gottfried
  - Romain Varlé. Catalogue raisonné des diverses curiosités du cabinet de feu son excellence Monseigneur le comte de Salm Reifferscheid, éveque de Tournay, composé d'une nombreuse collection d'histoire naturelle, de porcelaines anciennes & autres raretés, d'instrumens de phisique & de mécanique, de tableaux, estampes, de divers instrumens & Pièces de musique de différens maitres, & d'autres effets curieux …, 1771, 108, 93, 4 pages (Box 1, Item 006)
    Tournai (Belgium): Romain Varlé
    "Tables alphabetiques des auteurs de diverses Pièce de musique…qui composant cette belle collection," pp.88-93.
    Named collector(s): Salm, Franz Xaver von
  - Langford (Firm). Catalogue of the scarce, valuable and curious collection of music, manuscript and printed, of ... William Gostling ... which will be sold by auction ... on Monday the 26th of ... May 1777, etc., 1777-05-26, 20 pages (Box 1, Item 007)
    London (England): Langford (Firm)
    84, 89 lots (many more items). Copy of British Library, Hirsch IV:1083
    Named collector(s): Gostling, William
  - Christie and Ansell (London, England). Catalogue of the truly valuable and curious library of music late in the possession of Dr. William Boyce … consisting of all Dr. Green's curious and valuable manuscripts, with the greatest variety of excellent compositions for the church, chamber, and the theatre … which will be sold by auction … April 14, 1779 and two following days …, 1779-04-14, 32 pages (Box 1, Item 008)
    London (England): Christie and Ansell
    267 lots.
    Named collector(s): Boyce, William; Greene, Maurice
  - Unidentified. Catalogue de la musique de Monsieur Le Comte d'Ogny, 1786?, 168, 27 pages (Box 1, Item 009)
    Additional title: Catalogue de musique vocale
    France: unpublished manuscript
    British Library Hirsch cat. IV:1085. Thematic index. See Brook, no. 921. Title of second part of catalogue: catalogue de la musique non reliee qui se trouve dans les cartons de Monsieur le Comte d'Ogny.
    Named collector(s): Ogny, Claude François Marie Rigoley, Comte d'
  - Vogüé, Jacques Joseph François de, Bishop. Catalogue de la musique et des instrumens dépendans de la succession de m. de Vogüé évêque de Dijon, 1787-11-21, 24 pages (Box 1, Item 010)
    Dijon (France): J.B. Capel
    119 lots (many more items).
  - Müllers Schriften. Catalogus von Kupferstichen und Musicalien, welche den 5ten Jul. 1790. in loco convictorii hieselbst gegen baare Bezahlung in neue 2/3tel an den Meistbietenden offentlich verkaufet werden sollen, 1790-07-05, 24, 32 pages (Box 1, Item 011)
    Rostock (Germany): Müllers Schriften
    Bound with: Verzeichniss auserlesener theologischer, juristischer, medicinischer, historischer, moralischer, okonomischer und die schonen Wissenschaften einschlagender mehrentheils neuer gebundener Bucher in allerley Sprachen nebst einigen Musikalien und Kupferstichen, welche am 11 August und folgende Tage ... auf dem Eimbeckischen Hause offentlich verkauft werden sollen. Hamburg: Nicolaus Conrad Wormer, 1789 -- Verzeichniss einer Sammlung juristischer, medicinischer, historischer, okonomischer und in die scho¨nen Wissenschaften einschlagender gut conditionirter Bucher in allerley Sprachen nebst einigen Musicalien und Landcharten, welche den 30sten Septbr. und folgende Tage 1789 zu Schwerin in dem Hause wail. Hofrath Hertel gegen baare Bezahlung in N. Zwdr. meistbiethend verkauft werden sollen. Schwerin: publisher not identified, 1789.
  - Graham and Phillips. Catalogue of all the genuine elegant household furniture … and a variety of other valuable effects of a Gentleman, at his house, No. 6 Lisle Street, Leicester Fields, 1796-05-09, 24 pages (but many MS leaves interleaved) (Box 1, Item 012)
    London (England): Graham and Phillips
    All priced with buyers' names. Photocopy of GB-Lbl copy. Includes "Musical instruments, an undoubted violin by Stainer, a remarkably fine-toned upright piano by Stodart, a three-barrelled hand organ" and "A quantity of choice music bound and unbound".
  - Callcott, John Wall. Catalogue of his library with numerous definitions of musical terms and marginal comments on treatises and theorists' ideas, 1796-1807 (between), unnumbered pages (Box 1, Item 013)
    England: unpublished manuscript
    Copy of GB-Lbl Add. 17692. No overall title.
    Named collector(s): Callcott, John Wall
  - Smart's Musical Warehouse. Catalogue of the very curious and valuable musical library of antient and modern compositions, by the most eminent masters, from the sixteenth century to the present time: Consisting of madrigals, services, oratorios, odes, trios, concertos, canzonets, catches, motetts, anthems, operas, duets, sonatas, lessons, canons, masses, Psalms, cantatas, songs, serenetas, voluntaries, glees, &c. &c. by Tallis, Tye, Child, Gibbon, Purcell, Bird, Blow, Tudway, Bull, Morley, Carissimi, Leo, Feo, Pergolesi, Stradella, Lotti, Palistrina, Marcello, Stephani, Clari, Porpora, Handel, Haberman, Pepusch, Rameau, Richter, Gluck, Bach, Matherson, Claude le June, Philidore, and more than three hundred and fifty Italian, English, German, and French composers, the greatest part in excellent preservation, and collected through a series of years, with infinite care and judgment, by the Late W. and P. Hayes, doctors in music, oxon. N.B. Lot no. 377, is a choice and valuable collection of songs of Henry Lawes, written by himself, and valued by Dr. P. Hayes at 50. This capital collection is deposited at Smart's Music Warehouse, the corner of Argyll Street, Oxford Street, London, by appointment of the administrators. Where it may be viewed; the whole of which is made into lots, with the prices annexed in the catalogue, which will be delivered to the purchasers when the money is deposited, and the lots are to be taken away at their own expence. At the same time will be sold, a fine-toned harpsichord, warranted to be made by the celebrated Rooker of Antwerp, in perfect and high preservation, with a curious painting inside the lid., 1798?, 30 pages (Box 1, Item 014)
    London (England): Smart's Music Warehouse
    544 lots. Prices fixed and printed. Includes manuscript index from another source.
    Named collector(s): Hayes, William; Hayes, Philip
  - White, John, Mr.. Collection of old music. A catalogue of the greater part of the valuable collection of vocal and instrumental music, late the property of Dr. Samuel Howard, deceased: Consisting of services and anthems by the most esteemed authors of the last two centuries, viz. Tallis, Bird, Gibbons, Child, Rogers, Aldrich, Humphreys, Blow, Purcell, Clarke, Hall, Croft, Greene, Boyce, Kent, Hayes, Peputch, Travers, &c. with various Anthems, Te Deums, &c. by Handel:- Duets, Motets, Masses, &c. by Handel, Steffani, Bigaglia, Pergolesi, Hasse, Bononcini, Negri, Bassani, Palestrina, Carissimi, Jomelli, Uria, Foggia, Marcello, and Wassenaer; -operas by Handel, Bononcini, Lully, Porpora, Ziani, Torri, Pasquini, Sarro, &c. - cantatas by Scarlatti, Steffani, Pergolesi, Bononcini, Gasparini, Mancini, &c. &c. and Sonatas, Concertos, &c. by Geminiani, Corelli, Pugnani, Giordani, Sacchini, Bach, Abel, Haydn, Pleyel, Boccherini, Barthelemon, Kozeluch, &c. Among the scores are several original copies, and many other scarce and curious articles; which will be sold by auction by Mr. White, at his rooms, Storey's Gate, Great George Street, Westminster, on Tuesday, June 25, 1799, at twelve o'clock. To be viewed on Monday, and till the sale; when catalogues may be had, 1799-06-25, 11 pages (Box 1, Item 015)
    London (England): Mr. White
    156 lots. Copy of Hirsch IV:1083
    Named collector(s): Howard, Samuel
    Bound with: A Catalogue of the Scarce, Valuable and Curious Collection of Music, manuscript and printed, of ... William Gostling ... which will be sold by auction by Mess. Langford, ... on Monday the 26th of ... May 1777, etc.
  - Leigh, Sotheby and Son. Catalogue of a small, but very valuable collection of books, coins, medals, and music of a gentleman lately deceased, … which will be sold at auction … on March 9, 1802, and two following days …, 1802-03-09, 15 pages (Box 1, Item 016)
    London (England): Leigh, Sotheby and Son
    509 lots. With buyer's names & prices in manuscript.
  - Elssler, Johann. J. Haydn's Verzeichniss musicalischer Werke theils eigner, theils fremder Composition, 1802-1809, 80 unnumbered pages (Box 1, Item 017)
    Unidentified: unpublished manuscript
    737 items. British Museum Ms. Add. 32070. In the hand of his [Haydn's] amanuensis Elssler ... there are a few notes in Haydn's autograph
    Named collector(s): Haydn, Joseph
  - Gerber, Ernst Ludwig. Wissenschaftlich geordnetes Verzeichniss einer Sammlung von musikalischen Schriften, nebst einer Anzahl von Bildnissen berühmter Tonkünstler und musikalischer Schriftsteller, wie auch von verschiedenen Orgelprospecten, als ein Beitrag zur Literaturgeschichte der Musik, 1804, 43 pages (Box 1, Item 018)
    Sondershausen (Germany): Gedruckt mit Fleckschen Schriften
    Hundreds of items, unnumbered.
  - Koch Dehn?. Verzeichniss der von dem wail. Herrn Hofrath Findeisen hinterlassenen, grösstentheils juristischen Bücher, Landcharten und Musikalien: welche den 31sten März 1807 in dem Hause des Herrn Koch Dehn zu Schwerin gegen baare Bezahlung in N2/3tel öffentlich versteigert werden sollen, 1807-03-31, 82 pages (Box 1, Item 019)
    Schwerin (Germany): Koch Dehn?
    Sections separately lotted. Music, pp.60-82.
    Named collector(s): Findeisen, J. H., Hofrath
  - Werckmeister, Rudolph. Verzeichniss von ganz neuen Musikalien der beruhmtesten Komponisten des in- und Auslandes fur alle Instrumente und fur den Gesang desgleichen einiger Landcharten und Kupferstiche welche von Rudolph Werckmeister in Berlin, 1809, 172 pages (Box 1, Item 020)
    Berlin (Germany): Rudolph Werckmeister
    Sections separately lotted. Photocopy from copy in British Library.
  - Leigh and Sotheby. Catalogue of the entire library of the late Henry Compton Esq. of St. James's Palace ...: which will be sold by auction, by Leigh and Sotheby ... on Wednesday May 8, 1811 ... and five following days, etc., 1811-05-08, 41 pages (Box 1, Item 021)
    London (England): Leigh and Sotheby
    Buyers' names and prices written on the originals.
    Named collector(s): Compton, Henry; Sharpe, Granville; Sydney, John
    Bound with: A catalogue of the extensive and valuable music, printed and in manuscript, of the late Granville Sharpe (February 7 1814) -- A catalogie of the very extensive collection of music, the property of the late John Sydney (November 8 1813)
  - White, John, Mr.. Catalogue of the valuable and very fine collection of music printed and ms., of the late Charles Burney ... which will be sold by auction by Mr. White, at his rooms, Storey's Gate, Great George Street, Westminster, on Monday, the 8th of August, 1814, and following days, at twelve o'clock (pursuant to his will) …, 1814-08-08, 32 pages (Box 1, Item 022)
    Additional title: Late Dr. Burney's musical library
    822 lots. Some prices in MS.
    Named collector(s): Burney, Charles
    Bound with: Valuable Library of Music. A catalogue of the musical library of Robt. Smith, Esq. deceased.: which will be sold by auction, by Mr. White. on Tuesday, May the 18th, 1813, and following day, etc. -- The late Mr. Webbe's library of books, collection of music, and unpublished MSS. A catalogue of the entire and valuable library of books, and collection of music ... which will be sold at auction by Mr. White ... on Thursday July 4th, 1816 … -- A catalogue of the entire reserved part of vocal and instrumental music in score, of Edmund Tho. Warren Horne, Esq. ... to which is added the manuscript and printed music, the property of J. C. Davis, Esq. ... containing a complete collection of the works of Handel in score, likewise his musical instruments, which will be sold by auction by Leigh and S. Sotheby, ... on Monday, January 8, 1810, and two following days ... -- Musical Library. A Catalogue of the very extraordinary assemblage of manuscript and printed music, the pproperty of Dr. Kitchiner, containing the complete works of the best composers of all countries, among others equally valuable, the early productions and very rare Italian operas of Mr. Handel, Marcello's Psalms, Wm. Lawes' songs, MSS., a profusion on English, Italian, German, and French operas and treatises, &c. &c. ... which will be sold by auction by Leigh and S. Sotheby ... on Monday February 6, 1809 and four following days ... -- A catalogue of all the capital musical instruments, extensive and valuable collection of manuscript, and other music, by the most eminent composers, late the property of John Stanley ... Which will be sold by auction ... by Mr. Christie ... on Saturday the 24th of June, 1786.
  - Unidentified. Verzeichniss der von dem zu Giebichenstein bei Halle verstorbenen Herrn Kapellmeister Reichardt hinterlassenen Bücher und Musikalien, welche den 29sten April 1816 und in den darauf folgenden Tagen nachmittags um 2 Uhr zu Halle an den Meistbiethenden verkauft werden sollen, 1815, 110 pages (Box 2, Item 023)
    Halle (Germany): Unidentified
    Sections separately lotted. Original in the Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.
    Named collector(s): Reichardt, Johann Friedrich
  - Lippert, J. Ch.. Verzeichniss der musikalischen und andern Bücher, so wie auch der gedruckten und geschriebenen Musikalien des seligen … Dr. Türk, welche zu Halle an der Saale den 13. Januar 1817 ... versteigert werden sollen, etc., 1817-01-13, 72 pages (Box 2, Item 024)
    Halle (Germany): J. Ch. Lippert
    625 (music), 246 (general) lots. Published 1816.
    Named collector(s): Türk, Daniel Gottlob
  - Phillips, H., -1840. Catalogue of nearly the whole of the works of Signior Bianchi ... also, a small library of books on mathematics and other sciences, also, the twelve choice and celebrated violins and violincellos of the late Sir Patrick Blake … which will be sold by auction … 25th day of March, 1819 ... …25th of March, 1819., 1819-03-25, 12 pages (Box 2, Item 025)
    Additional title: Musical compositions of the late celebrated Signior Francisco Bianchi, and the valuable musical instruments and music of the late Sir Patrick Blake
    London (England): Phillips (Firm), Printed by J. Davy
    149 lots. Interleaves bear buyers' names and prices.
    Named collector(s): Bianchi, Francisco; Blake, Patrick
  - F. C. Huth. Verzeichniss der von dem verstorbenen Doctor und Musikdirector Forkel in Göttingen nachgelassenen Bücher und Musikalien: welche den 10ten May 1819 und an den folgenden Tagen nachmittags von 1 bis 2 Uhr und abends von 6 bis 8 Uhr in der Wohnung des Univ. Gerichts-Procur. und Notars Fr. Justus Schepeler an der Jüdenstrasse in Göttingen meistbietend verkauft werden, 1819-05-10, 200 pages (Box 2, Item 026)
    Göttingen (Germany): F. C. Huth
    1730, 450, 39, 1086, 506, 40, 15 lots (many more items). Copy of Hirsch 4:1082.
    Named collector(s): Forkel, Johann Nikolaus
  - Hermann. Index Librorum ex omni scientia lectissi morum integritate et nitore insignium, quos collegit C. F. T. Schwencke, per XXX annos et amplius in Joanneo, quod Hamburgi floret, Cantor et chori musici director, Publice vendentur … d. 25 Augusti 1823, 1823-08-25, 130 pages (Box 2, Item 027)
    Hamburg (Germany): Hermann
    Sections separately lotted. Bound with: Berndes, J. J., auctioneer. "Verzeichniss der von dem verstorbenen Herrn…C.F.G. Schwenke aus allen Fächern der Tonkunst…welche am 30sten August und folgende Tage…verkauf Weden soll." 79 pages, 1432 lots.
    Named collector(s): Schwencke, C. F. G. (Christian Friedrich Gottlieb)
  - Adlers Erben (Rostock, Germany). Verzeichniss der von dem verstorbenen academ. Musiklehrer, Organisten Göpel in Rostok nachgelassenen Musikalien, musicalischen Instrumente und Bücher: welche am 1sten Septbr. 1824 ... öffentlich ... durch den Auctions, Secretair Uebele, 1824-09-01, 51 pages (Box 2, Item 028)
    Rostock (Germany): Adlers Erben
    Sections separately lotted.
    Named collector(s): Göpel, Johann Andreas
    Bound with: Verzeichniss von Musicalien: insgesamt von den berühmtesten Componisten nach alphabetischer Ordnung: welche den 20 Merz 1777 zu Stade auf dem Rathhaus öffentlich verkauft werden sollen (1776) -- Appendix gedruckter und geschriebener Musicalien von den berühmtesten Meistern: nebst einigen Büchern welche den 25. Oct. 1780 auf dem Eimbeckischen Hause öffentlich verkauft werden sollen (1780).
  - Sotheby and Son. Catalogue of the bibliographical and other collections of eminent literary men, forming a most interesting and curious series of sale and privately printed catalogues of literary property, from the commencement of the last century to the present time; collected together with the greatest difficulty: the whole in the choicest condition. Which will be sold by auction, by Mr. Sotheby and son ... on Wednesday, July 27th …, 1831-07-27, 49 pages (Box 2, Item 029)
    London (England): Sotheby and Son
    320 lots (hundreds more items). With buyers' names and prices fetched. Possibly incomplete? Cataloging records show 60 pages.
  - Auctionsverwalter Behre. Verzeichniss der von dem Herrn Justizrath und Doctor medicinae Ludw. Sam. Died. Mutzenbecher nachgelassenen musikalischen Bibliothek: bestehend aus einer reichen sammlung der vorzüglichesten Musikalien und einer bedeutenden Anzahl Werke der alten und neuern berühmten Tonkünstler: welche den II. Februar 1839 und folgende Tage nach Beendigung der Auction der Hauptbibliothek in dem Hause des Verstorben, Langestr. No. 9 durch den Herrn Auctionsverwalter Behre öffentlich verkauft werden sollen, 1839-02-11, 89 pages (Box 2, Item 030)
    Altona (Germany): Hammerich & Lesser
    1276 lots. Copy from Brussels, Bibliothèque Albert I.
    Named collector(s): Mutzenbecher, Ludwig Samuel Dieterich
  - J. Fletcher (Firm). Catalogue of a choice collection of valuable music, manuscript and printed, consisting of the manuscript scores, many of which are unpublished, together with a great variety of printed songs and other music, the property of the late celebrated melodist and favorite composer, Mr. James Hook, also a collection of very valuable musical instruments … which will be sold by auction … July 5th, 1842, 1842-07-05, 9 pages (Box 2, Item 031)
    Additional title: Music and musical instruments
    London (England): J. Fletcher (Firm)
    177 lots.
    Named collector(s): Hook, James
  - Santini, Fortunato. Select catalogue of the curious M.S.S. in the Library of the Abbate Santini at Romr. Kindly brought from Italy to me by … Price, Esq., 1843. Vincent Novello …, 1843, 9 leaves (Box 2, Item 032)
    "Presented to the library of the Musical Antiquarian Society by V.N. 1844." Accompanied by article by Klaus Kindler: Zur problematik der Masi-Handschriften in der Santini-Sammlung in Munster (Westf.)
    Named collector(s): Santini, Fortunato